Folder inventory for the Dawn Eichenlaub historic preservation research collection, 1965-1983 MS2170
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Dawn Eichenlaub historic preservation research collection
1965-1983
1976-1978
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Eichenlaub, Dawn Monica
MS2170
2.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains the research files of Dawn Eichenlaub. The type of document include legal cases, brochures, meeting agendas, reports, organizational charts, newsletters, and newspaper articles. These materials date from 1965-1983 with the bulk falling between 1976-1978. The subjects relate to historic preservation primarily within the D.C. metropolitan area and are mostly for different historic preservation organizations working in the city. These organizations include both federal agencies and non-profits.
Biography
Dawn Eichenlaub was a 1983 graduate of GW. Her masters thesis is titled Rhodes Tavern and Square 224: 1978-1983 A Case Study of Preservation Practices in Washington, D.C.
Arrangement
The folders within this collection are maintained in the order in which they were donated. The folders appear to have a semblance of alphabetical order by folder title through most of box 3, but the order is only loosely in alphabetical order for half of box 3, box 4 and box 5.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dawn Eichenlaub, 1983
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the research files of Dawn Eichenlaub. The type of document include legal cases, brochures, meeting agendas, reports, organizational charts, publications, newsletters, and newspaper articles. These materials date from 1965-1983 with the bulk falling between 1976-1978. The subjects relate to historic preservation primarily within the D.C. metropolitan area and are mostly for different historic preservation organizations working in the city. These organizations include both federal agencies and non-profits.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Urban renewal; Urbanization; Historic preservation; Preservation and restoration; Historic buildings; Historic buildings -- Conservation and restoration; Don't Tear It Down
- Advisory Council on Historic Preservation - fact sheet, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Advisory Council on Historic Preservation - procedures for the protection of historical and cultural properties, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Advisory Council on Historic Preservation - funding assistance, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Advisory Council on Historic Preservation - guidelines for state historic preservation legislation historic preservation workshop, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Advisory Council on Historic Preservation - report = special issue (v. 4 #8), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- American Institute of Architects (AIA) - library bibliography: library holdings, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- American Institute of Architects (AIA) - adaptive reuse: extending the life of old buildings (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- American Institute of Historical Preservation - information, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Architectural Heritage Foundation - subscription: "The Revolving Fund Handbook", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Birmingham Union - for the restoration of Pittsburgh's Southside (newsletter), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Baltimore City Dept. of Planning - bibliography of urban reinvestment and displacement, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Brownstone Revival Committee - application (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Capital Hill Restoration Society - News (newsletter), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Center for Washington Area Studies - Washington Works (newsletter), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Center for the Visual Environment - brochure, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- City Musuem Projections - newslettter, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Commission of Fine Arts - information sheet, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Govt of D.C. - Commission on Residential Mortgage Investement: "A Preliminary Report", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Govt of D.C. - Dept. of Housing and Community Development: "Materials on the Tax Form", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Govt of D.C. - Joint Committee on Landmarks of the National Capitol: "Statement of Functions and Membership", undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- D.C.Municipal Planning Office - "Wash. D.C.: Planning a City for People" (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- D.C. Preservation League, newsletter, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- D.C. Redevelopment Land Agency - a bibliographic tour of Washington D.C., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- D.C. Register - tax information, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - Board of Directors meeting agendas, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - Board of Directors letters to board members, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - Chinatown WDC's Chinese Community, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - Chinatown fundraising plans, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - Chinatown survey, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - Flyer of events, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - fundraising proposal and letter to appeal, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - membership information, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - newsletters, 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - news clippings, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - National Capital Planning: Commission's Report on Historical Buildings, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - organizational plan, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - Downtown Project Proposal, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - general report, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Don't Tear It Down (DTID) - "A walking tour: Preservation and planning in the downtown", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Eichenlaub Capital Hill notes, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Federal Home Loan Bank Board journal v. 8 #8, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- GWU -bibliography reading lists for courses, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Kentucky Heritage order form, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- L'Enfant Trust - voluntary preservation project, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Library of Congress - assortment of brochures, guides, indexes, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Loyola College -readings on historic preservation, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Maryland Historical Trust brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Maryland Historical Trust conference materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Maryland Historical Trust guides and information on historical preservation, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments - brochures, misc., undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments - air quality index, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments - list of publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments - regional directory, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments - water resource planning board brochure, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments - annual report "Three Million Reasons", 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments - metropolitan memo "a bi-weekly report", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments - Report from national capital region: "Transportation Planning Board Progress", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Metropolitan Washington Planning and Housing Association - newsletter, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- National Archives - a researcher's guide to the National Archives, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- National Building Musuem - public law 96-515, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- National Building Musuem - Blueprints (newsletter), 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- National Capital Downtown Committee - Downtown Progress Report, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- National Endowment for the Arts - grants: "Downtown Reinvestment by Design", 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- National Register of Historic Places - sources of preservation funds, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - application forms, community preservation workshop, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - a bibliography of neighborhood leaders, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - brochure "only you can help yourself", 1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - reports and bulletins, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - charts: "Historical Preservation litigation" and "Resolved or Pending ", 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - grant reports, program brochures, information, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - case: "Easement vs Zoning: preservation tools", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - law developments, tax information act, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - newsletter, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - newsletter: Preservation Action, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - resources library resources in W.D.C. relating to historical preservation and guide to resources used in research, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTFHP) - urban conservationand federally assisted economic development in cities: putting it all together, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Old-House Journal newsletter, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Partners for livable places: intro: "The Ethic Behind Partners for livable places", undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Preservation Action - newsletters and brochure "The National Lobby for the Built Environment, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Preservation / Design group brochure, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Preservation Reports, Inc. Neighborhood Conservation and Reinvestment newsletter, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Preservation Resource Group, Inc. bibliography attached with notes "Principles of Architectural Conservation", undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Shlaes and Co. financing preservation in the private market, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Society for the Industrial Archeology newsletter, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development - fact sheets "Home Improvement Loan Program" and "Aiding Lower Incom Famliles", 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development - guidelines for draft rehabilitation part 10, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Dupont Circle - map, historical events, and soci-economic description, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Dupont Circle - paper clippings, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Board of Zoning Adjustment of D.C. memorandum of Joint Commitee on landmarks of the national capital on admissibility of testimony", 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Joint Commitee on landmarks of the National Capital - Dupont Circle Historic District application to amend and redesignate, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Georgetown Waterfront newsletter clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Citizens Association of Georgetown- dates and historical events, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Georgetown Waterfront - newsletter and clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Georgetown Waterfront - plan for development and preservation, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Logan Circle - historical preservation area, summary of consultant's reports, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Neighborhood 7th and Pennsylviania Ave. - letter concerning blocking the demolition of buildings, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Neighborhood 7th St. NW - demolition notice and hearing testimony (11 testimony supports, 6 proposed orders to delay demolition in square 457, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Neighborhood 7th St. NW - newspaper clippings "House Votes Ave. Funds", 1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Neighborhood 7th St. NW - application (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Scope and Contents
  written on folder "application for demolition of historic buildings: recommended to the State Historic Preservation officer persuant to D.C. regulation 73-25 (1976) and neighborhor. 7th St. NW proposed order of demolition by DC Govt. to issuance of delay permit to raise a building in lot 820 (1976) and 7th St. NW - Govt. of D.C. order to delay issuance of a permit to reaise (1976)"
- Neighborhood 7th and Pennyslvania notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Neighborhood 7th NW - a preservation study of 401-417 7th St. NW, WDC, by the Preservation Design Group, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Neighborhood 7th and Pennyslvania Ave. - survey plan (cont.), undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
- U.S. Dept. of the Interior - selected bibliographies and reading lists, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- U.S. Dept. of the Interior - preservation briefs 1;6, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- U.S. Dept. of the Interior - national register of historic places (brochures), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- U.S. Dept. of the Interior - chart of the Office of Archeology and Historic Preservation (chain of command), undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- U.S. Dept. of the Interior - fact sheet, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- U.S. Dept. of the Interior - historic preservation grants-in-aid (brochures), undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Dept. of Housing and Urban Development - HUD challenge (journal), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Dept. of the Interior - House Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs (list), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Dept. of the Interior - National Register of Historic Places (Heritage Conservation Recreation Services) and publications - How to Complete National Register Forms, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Preservation and Taxation newsleter and newspaper clippings, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Dept. of the Interior - Supplement 11593 (newsletter), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Dept. of the Interior - establishment of a Heritage and Recreation Service (proposal), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Dept. of the Interior - National Heritage Trust task force (reports 1,2,3), 1977 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Dept. of the Interior - drafts: "Exterior Cleaning of Historic Masonry Buildings", "Rectified Photography and Photo Drawings for Hist. Pres." and "X-ray examin. of hist. structures", 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Dept. of the Interior - standards or rehabilitation and guidelines for rehabilitating historic buildings, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Dept. of the Interior - tax recommendations, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Dept. of the Interior - Office of Archeology and Historic Preservation - telephone directory, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Urban Reinvestment Tax Force -articles on Neighborhood Housing Services, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Urban Reinvestment Tax Force - Baltimore Neighborhood Housing Services brochures, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Urban Reinvestment Tax Force - map of office locations of Neighborhood Housing Services, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Urban Reinvestment Tax Force - Neighborhood Preservation newsletter, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Urban Reinvestment Tax Force - Neighborhood Housing Service announcement, introductions, and applications, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Urban Reinvestment Tax Force - Neighborhood Housing Service historic preservation: resource opportunities, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
- U.S. Govt staff report on Sub-Committee on Downtown Landmarks meeting, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- University of Vermont dept. of history - bibliography: recommended reading for the Community Conservation workshop, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
- University of Vermont Natural Resources Council - possibilities: a quarterly news journal, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Urban Institute- publications catalog, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Urban Land Institute - publications, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Metropolitan Washington Board of Trade - brochure and newsletter, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Washington Institute of Historical Preservation - Washington Landmarks newsletter, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- National state and federal authorities - notes on the landmark case of Berman v. Parker, 348 U.S. 26, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
- The Supreme Court of DC - Crandell v. Crandell (filed 1893), undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Supreme Court - Penn Central Transportation Co. v. The City of New York, October Term 1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Legal case - Rivers v. U.S., undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Alexandria legal case - leg. code 2180 and legal code ordinance, 1965-1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  note on folder "Boston Mass and Chicago legal code ordinance - municipal code of Illinois (1969) and S.C. legal code ordinance - purposes of preservation ordinances and mass hall, and Michigan legal code ordinances - Historical District ordinacne and legal leg - New Orleans (1969/76) and Rochester (1969) and Sacremento City code and Savannah, Ga. and legal DC code ordinance- public law 89-326 (1965)"
- Legal code - National Historic Preservation Act of 1966: public law 89-665 (1966) and legal code - National Historic Pres. Act (1966) (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Legal misc., undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
- notes misc., undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  General
  These notes are handwritten